Guide to the Bonnie Lee Black papers, 1981-2015 RL.11288
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Bonnie Lee Black papers
1981-2015
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Black, Bonnie Lee
RL.11288
36 Linear Feet 23 boxes (numbering skips 18)
Bonnie Lee Black is a writer, editor, writing teacher, and chef who has worked both domestically and internationally. The collection centers primarily on her work as a writer, as a member of the Peace Corps in Gabon, as a professor in New Mexico, and as the creator of an economic development project in Mali aimed at teaching local seamstresses the art of patchwork quilt-making.
Arrangement
Materials are arranged in the order in which they were received. Please note that there is no box 18 in this collection; the numbering skips from 17 to 19.
Content Description
The Bonnie Lee Black papers comprise personal correspondence, materials from her time working in Mali, teaching materials from her time as a professor at the University of New Mexico-Taos, documents from her experience in the Peace Corps in Gabon and Mali, and materials generated from two of her books, How to Make an African Quilt and How to Cook a Crocodile.
Biographical / Historical
Bonnie Lee Black spent 30 years as a writer and over 20 years as an educator both in the US and overseas. She has published three memoirs, Somewhere Child, How to Make an African Quilt and How to Cook a Crocodile. She has worked as a health and nutrition volunteer for the Peace Corps in Gabon. Subsequently, she pursued an economic development project geared towards educating Malian seamstresses about quilt-making. In 2001, she began her career teaching English and writing at the University of New Mexico-Taos. She continues to write for her blog, "WOW Factor."
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Peace Corps (U.S.) -- Gabon; Peace Corps (U.S.) -- Mali; Cooking -- Gabon; Higher Education -- New Mexico; Quilting -- Mali; Gabon -- Description and travel; Mali -- Description and travel; Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture
- Book materials, 1997-2010
  - How to cook a crocodile: A memoir with recipes, 1997-2010
    - How to Cook a Crocodile, 2010 (Box 7)
    - Crocodile manuscript (Box 10)
    - How to Cook a Crocodile, a Memoir with Recipes, proposal (Box 10)
    - How to Cook a Crocodile, chapters reviewed by AULA mentors, 2005 (Box 10)
    - How to Cook a Crocodile manuscript, 2007 (Box 10)
    - How to Cook a Crocodile proposal (Box 10)
    - Book II - New York Times clips of relevance, 2002-2005 (Box 11)
    - Book II - emails/advice/miscellaneous, 1996-2007 (Box 11)
    - Book II - Christmas letters, 1997 (Box 11)
    - Book II - Chantal Chanson (puppets), 1997-2004 (Box 11)
    - Book II - table of contents and chapter to-dos, 2007 (Box 11)
    - Book II - foreword, 1998-2007 (Box 11)
    - Book II - notes/drafts/letters, 1996-2006 (Box 11)
    - Book II - 1st drafts, 2003-2004 (Box 11)
    - Cover photos (Box 12)
    - Book II - Zimbabwe, 1993-2007 (Box 12)
    - Book II - Plus Belle, 1998-2007 (Box 12)
    - Book II - Women's Center, 1998-2007 (Box 12)
    - Book II - Lulu, 1998-2007 (Box 12)
    - Book II - Youssef, part 2 (photos, career), "Photographe", 1996-2007 (Box 12)
    - Book II - Compost Queen exposé, 1996-2007 (Box 12)
    - Book II - Vanilla Sister, 2001-2007 (Box 12)
    - Book II - Venez Voir, polio drive, 1998-2007 (Box 12)
    - Book II - notes, 1996-2007 (Box 12)
    - Book II - front and back matter (Box 12)
    - Book II - photos and miscellaneous (Box 12)
    - Book II - Crocodiles (research/theme), 2006 (Box 12)
    - Book II - Diner, 1997 (Box 13)
    - Book II - The Wedding Cake (Antoinette), 1996-2006 (Box 13)
    - Book II - Rain/Heat, 1996-2007 (Box 13)
    - Book II - Mefloquine Dreams, 1997-2007 (Box 13)
    - Book II - Friday Night Brights, 1999-2007 (Box 13)
    - Book II - Gabon Garbet, 1996-2007 (Box 13)
    - Book II - OCTRA Classes, 1998-2007 (Box 13)
    - Book II - Mapping Africa, future plans, 2001-2007 (Box 13)
    - Book II - Love Letters, 1996-2007 (Box 13)
    - Book II - Exposés (Work), 2007 (Box 13)
    - Book II - break-in, 1997-2006 (Box 13)
    - Book II - Cooking, Youssef, 2002-2006 (Box 14)
    - Book II - Morgan, 1997-2007 (Box 14)
    - Book II - Bev/Church, 2002-2007 (Box 14)
    - Book II - Cancer scare, 2004 (Box 14)
    - Book II - Manioc, 1997-2006 (Box 14)
    - Book II - Sister Truth, 1998 (Box 14)
    - Book II - A thank you to Paul, 1997 (Box 14)
    - Book II - World Wise Schools, 1996 (Box 14)
    - Book II - The Still of the Night, 1998-2004 (Box 14)
    - Book II - Memba, 1996-2004 (Box 14)
    - Book II - Discovering Beans, 1998 (Box 14)
    - Book II - Pompano, 1995-2006 (Box 14)
    - Book II - Petit a Petit, 2005 (Box 14)
    - Book II - How to Cook a Crocodile, 2004-2006 (Box 14)
    - Book II - The Martha Stewart of Gabon (decorating), 1997-2004 (Box 14)
  - How to make an African quilt: the story of the Patchwork Project of Segou, Mali, 2000-2009
    - Quilting the Quilt, 2001 (Box 4)
    - Comfort Quilts, undated (Box 3)
    - How to Make an African Quilt, 2009 (Box 4)
    - Patchwork: a Memoir of Mali, undated (Box 4)
    - Mali book - for final chapters, 2009 (Box 5)
    - Book III - Mali, Graduation, 2009 (Box 5)
    - Book III - Mali, Final Exam, 2009 (Box 5)
    - Book III - Mali, Patchwork Project, 2009 (Box 5)
    - Patchwork Project, 2000 (Box 23)
- Peace Corps, 1991-2010
  - Peace Corps., 1994-2007 (Box 1)
  - General Correspondence from Gabon, 1996-1998 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with Marty Cooper, 1996-1998 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence from Marty C. from Gabon, 1996-1997 (Box 1)
  - Letters to Heather from Gabon, 1996-1998 (Box 1)
  - Letters to Paul Matteo from Gabon, 1996-1998 (Box 1)
  - Gabon, Zimbabwe, Mali, 1991-2002 (Box 2)
  - Peace Corps., 1995-1997 (Box 2)
  - Peace Corps., 1996-1998 (Box 2)
  - Journals, 1996-1998 (Box 2)
  - Journals, 1997-2007 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence from Mali, 2009-2010 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence after returning to the U.S. from Mali, 2000-2002 (Box 20)
  - Mali journals, 1998-2001; 4 folders (Box 20)
- Writings and professional materials, 1996-2015; Bonnie Lee Black is a writer, editor, professor, and chef whose highly varied work transcended continents. The collection centers primarily on her work as a member of the Peace Corps. in Gabon, a professor in New Mexico, and as the creator of an economic development project in Mali aimed at teaching local seamstresses the art of patchwork quilt-making.
  Scope and Contents
  The Bonnie Lee Black papers are arranged by folder in the order they were received. The folders comprise personal correspondence, materials from her time working in Mali, resources from her time as a professor at the University of New Mexico Taos, documents from her experience in the Peace Corps. in Gabon, and notes regarding her two memoirs, How to Make an African Quilt and How to Cook a Crocodile.
  Biographical / Historical
  Before her retirement at the age of 70 in 2015, Bonnie Lee Black spent 30 years as a writer and over 20 years as an educator both in the US and overseas. She has written two memoirs, How to Make an African Quilt and How to Cook a Crocodile. Her passion for food and cooking led her to work as a health and nutrition volunteer for the Peace Corps. in Gabon. Two years later, she pursued an economic development project geared towards educating Malian seamstresses about quilt-making. In 2001, she began her career as a professor at the University of New Mexico Taos, where she taught until 2015. Today, she is an active writer for her blog, "WOW Factor."
  - Imagining Helen draft, 2012 (Box 3)
  - Progress logs, 2014-2015 (Box 3)
  - Blueberry Muffins, 2005-2006 (Box 5)
  - Puppets (Box 5)
  - Sweet Tarts for my Sweethearts - Sallie Bingham blog post, 2014 (Box 5)
  - Ninth Annual Taos Summer Writers' Conference, 2007 (Box 6)
  - New Mexico Press Women contest, 2015 (Box 6)
  - Genre Writing Workshops, 2006 (Box 6)
  - Clippings and articles (Box 6)
  - Resumes and letters of recommendation (Box 6)
  - Notes, 2002 (Box 6)
  - Group topics, ideas, 2002 (Box 6)
  - Bakery, 2001 (Box 6)
  - Isabelle's "Morocco Saga", 2001 (Box 6)
  - Read it to the Mountain (Box 6)
  - Self-publishing and print-on-demand (Box 6)
  - Jonah Straus, literary agent, 2008 (Box 6)
  - Algonquin Books, 2008 (Box 6)
  - My Turn (newspaper column), 2008 (Box 6)
  - Dixon Studio Tour, 2002-2003 (Box 8)
  - Closing Time, 2008 (Box 8)
  - Quilting (Box 8)
  - Museum of American Folk Art, 2000-2001 (Box 8)
  - Antioch University MFA in Creative Writing, 2004-2007 (Box 8)
  - Bread project, 1997-2007 (Box 11)
  - Mountains essay and Blood, 2005 (Box 13)
  - 4th packet for Bernadette, 2006 (Box 13)
  - Sans Frigo, 1996-2005 (Box 14)
  - Anthology - Never Too Late, Machete Lesson, 1996-2003 (Box 14)
  - Remarkable Women of Taos - Book (Box 16)
  - Nonnie's favorite (easy) recipes - a legacy cookbook (Box 16)
  - Legacy Cookbook (Box 16)
  - Storied Recipes Cookbook (Box 16)
  - Chokecherries Anthology (Box 16)
  - The Year of the Blue Jay - an anthology (Box 16)
  - Planners and notebooks, 2002-2004 (Box 20)
- University of New Mexico - Taos, 2005-2010
  - English 323: Course at UNM Taos, 2011 (Box 9)
  - UNM Taos Faculty Orientation, 2010 (Box 9)
  - UNM Taos: English 223, 2010 (Box 9)
  - Creative Non-Fiction (CNF) 224, UNM Taos, 2012 (Box 9)
  - Teaching and course evaluations, 2005-2006 (Box 15)
  - University of New Mexico Taos course evaluations, 2005-2010 (Box 15)
  - Student feedback, 2006 (Box 15)
  - Howl: The Voice of UNM Taos, 2010 (Box 15)
- Photographs, scrapbooks, and textiles, 1985-2013
  - Photographs, 1985-2013
    - Photographs (Box 8)
    - Photo Album (Box 16)
    - Photographs of Bonnie Lee Black in Africa, undated (Box 19)
    - Travel photos, 1999-2000; 2 folders (Box 21)
    - Patchwork/Ty's quilt/Chez moi photos, 2000 (Box 21)
    - Mali and New Mexico photos, 2001 (Box 22)
    - Mali photos, undated
    - Peace Corps, Gabon photos, 1996-1998
    - Patchwork Project photos, undated
    - Peace Corps service, site visit photos, 1996
    - Gabon photos, 1997
    - Negatives, undated
    - Mali photos with negatives, undated
    - Zimbabwe photos, 1996-1997
    - Photos of Bonnie Lee Black, undated
    - Mali albums, 1999-2000
    - Dixon, New Mexico house and animals, 2008
    - Dixon, New Mexico photos, 2006-2008 (Box 23)
    - Photographs, 1996-2013 (Box 23)
    - Photographs, 2001-2003 (Box 23)
    - Photographs, 1985-2004 (Box 23)
    - Luisa's wedding weekend, Washington, DC, 1993 (Box 23)
  - Scrapbooks, 1986-1996
    - Scotland scrapbook, 1986 (Box 19)
    - Paris scrapbook, 1993 (Box 19)
    - Gabon scrapbook, 1996 (Box 19)
  - Textiles, 1999 and undated
    - Printed t-shirt, "Pour une monde plus propre, Mali 99", 1999 (Box 24)
    - Quilted pillow cover in West African brocade, 18" x 18" (Box 24)
    - Batik panel with African scene in blue, purple, and green, 35" x 52" (Box 24)
    - West African woven indigo fabric panel, 40" x 57" (Box 24)
- Printed materials, 1981-2012
  - Somewhere Child unpublished proofs, 1981 (Box 17)
  - Somewhere Child with dust jacket, 1981 (Box 17)
  - Somewhere Child with presentation binding, 1981 (Box 17)
  - A Matter of Choice: 25 people who transformed their lives, 2004 (Box 17)
    General
    Includes "Machete Lessons" by Bonnie Lee Black
  - Under the Sun, volume XV, no. 1, Summer 2010 (Box 17)
    Includes "Weather Report" by Bonnie Lee Black
  - Alimentum: The literature of food, issues 5 & 13, 2007-2012 (Box 20)
    Issue 5 contains "Pain Americain" by Bonnie Lee Black
- Journals, 2009-2014
  - Journals, 2009 (Box 20)
  - Journals, 2010-2014; 9 folders